<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The triumph of the Church over water and fire. Or A thankfull gratulation for that miraculous deliverance of the Church and state of Great Britaine, from the Romish Tophet: or, that barbarous and savage Powder-plot As it was delivered (for substance) in a sermon at Blacke Fryers in London on the fifth of November. 1625. By Theodor Hering, minister of the Word of God.</title>
            <title>Triumph of the Church over water and fire.</title>
            <author>Herring, Theodore, 1596-1645.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 94 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03080</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13204</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104029</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839770</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839770</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4221</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03080)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4221)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1602:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The triumph of the Church over water and fire. Or A thankfull gratulation for that miraculous deliverance of the Church and state of Great Britaine, from the Romish Tophet: or, that barbarous and savage Powder-plot As it was delivered (for substance) in a sermon at Blacke Fryers in London on the fifth of November. 1625. By Theodor Hering, minister of the Word of God.</title>
                  <title>Triumph of the Church over water and fire.</title>
                  <author>Herring, Theodore, 1596-1645.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 43, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I[ohn] D[awson] for Nicholas Bourne, at the south entrance of the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The triumph of the Church over fire and water.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gunpowder Plot, 1605 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4221:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TRIVMPH OF THE CHVRCH OVER <hi>WATER</hi> AND <hi>FIRE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OR A Thankfull <hi>Gratulation</hi> for that Miraculous Deliverance of the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> of <hi>Great Britaine,</hi> from the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Tophet:</hi> or, that barbarous and ſavage <hi>Powder-plot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As it was delivered (for ſubſtance) in a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon at <hi>Blacke Fryers</hi> in <hi>London</hi> on the <hi>fifth of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember.</hi> 162<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> THEODOR HERING, <hi>Miniſter of the Word of</hi> GOD.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ISAI. 29.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Woe vnto them that digge deepe, to hide their councell from the Lord; for their workes are in darkeneſſe, and they ſay, Who ſeeth vs? Who knoweth vs?</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 66.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Wee went into fire and into water, but thou broughtest vs out into a wealthy Land.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>I. D.</hi> for <hi>Nicholas Bourne,</hi> at the South entrance of the <hi>Royall Exchange.</hi> 1625.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4221:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4221:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, IAMES, LORD LEE; Baron of <hi>Lee,</hi> Lord High Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> one of the Lords of his MAIESTIES moſt Honorable privie <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell,</hi> my dearly honored PATRON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HONORABLE;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is an <hi>Aphoriſme of State,</hi> delivered by a great and wiſe <hi>King; When the Righteous are exalted, the Citty reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth.</hi> A good Man, (eſpecially, if a <hi>Great Man</hi>) is a common Good. Where <hi>Goodneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:4221:3"/> and Greatneſſe,</hi> meete together, that <hi>Happie coniunction</hi> promiſeth a <hi>Gracious aſpect.</hi> Giue me leaue (being received into and ſhrou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnder the winges of <hi>your Honors Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection</hi>) to congratulate that <hi>High Honor</hi> which <hi>His Maieſty</hi> hath ſo worthily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred on <hi>your Lord-ſhip.</hi> I know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Place</hi> doth more <hi>Honor</hi> the <hi>Man,</hi> or the <hi>Man</hi> the <hi>Place.</hi> Your Honors <hi>Wiſedome, Experience, Iuſtice, Gravitie, Pietie,</hi> what good doe they not preſage? If the world faile not exceedingly of their expectation, none more like, to doe <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> and his <hi>Country</hi> better ſervice. Your <hi>Honor</hi> hath the prayers and hearts of <hi>the beſt,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore need not (being armed with ſuch a <hi>Coate of Male</hi>) feare the calumnies or oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of <hi>the worſt.</hi> For my-ſelfe, your <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors</hi> favour and countenance afforded me in private, hath obliged me to a publike Gratulation, and emboldened me to dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate theſe my Labours to your Honor (to whom I haue given my ſelfe) as being a <hi>chiefe Member</hi> of this <hi>State,</hi> and therefore knowing the ſtate of this Story, better
<pb facs="tcp:4221:3"/> then my rude draught can pourtray it; wherein your Honor ſhall ſee the <hi>Combat, Conflict,</hi> and <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> as of the Church in generall, ſo of <hi>this Church, this State</hi> in ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. Never any Nation ſo <hi>embroiled,</hi> ſo <hi>entan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled,</hi> came off ſo <hi>faire.</hi> Never any intended bloudy <hi>Tragedy,</hi> ſhut vp with ſuch a reall ioyfull <hi>Cataſtrophe.</hi> The <hi>Matter</hi> cannot but yeeld delight to a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> eſpecially to an <hi>Engliſh-man:</hi> If the <hi>Manner</hi> pleaſe not, I haue done my endevour to cloath it with the beſt Suit my homely <hi>Wardrope</hi> could affoord, more in ſo ſhort a time, and on ſo ſuddaine a warning I cannot promiſe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Grecians</hi> delivered it as a Prover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biall Precept, that who ever ſpeakes to <hi>Great Men,</hi> his words muſt be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Suauiſsima &amp; breuiſsima,</hi> as wee Engliſh it, <hi>Short and ſweete:</hi> What my Diſcourſe wants in the one, (if it be not ſo ſweete as I could wiſh it) it ſhall make vp in the other, and be as ſhort as your <hi>Honors</hi> more weightie employments require, to which I remit your <hi>Honor,</hi> wiſhing <hi>many a happie New-yeare</hi> to your Noble <hi>Lordſhip,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:4221:4"/> and my Honorable Good <hi>Lady,</hi> with all encreaſe of Honor and Happineſſe here, and here-after, remaining</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your <hi>Honors</hi> humbly devoted in all faithfull obſervance, <hi>THEOD: HERING.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4221:4"/>
            <head>¶ To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, Little did I dreame, that theſe priuate Meditations, intended only for a particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, ſhould be made thus publicke, to the view of the whole world. <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo proponit, Deus diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponit,</hi> Man purpoſeth, but God diſpoſeth. Importunitie wrung them from me, not onely beſide, but againſt my intention. My pleas were many, if they might haue beene heard. The ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of time allotted for preparation, multitude of other diſtractions, which would ſcarce giue me leaue either to write what I had Preached, or to review what I had written before the publication.</p>
            <p>The curioſitie of the times, and various humour of men, what one likes, another diſlikes, one thinkes it too curious, another too careleſſe; one too facile, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther too obſcure, one too looſe, another too elaborate. So impoſsible is it for any one man, to pleaſe all men.
<pb facs="tcp:4221:5"/> The ſame ſentence which pleaſeth one, diſlikes another; the ſame man, that receiues content this houre, is out of charitie the next; ſo various is man in his thoughts, ſo vnconſtant in his cenſures to others and himſelfe. Adde to this beſide the fickleneſſe of ſome, the perverſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of others, who <hi>Malchus</hi>-like, heare all with the <hi>left eare;</hi> and as if the right hand were withered, like <hi>Ieroboams,</hi> take all with <hi>the left.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If ſome paſſages accord (in ſubſtance) with cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine materiall poynts that are delivered of other Writers, though never ſo different in the carriage and circumſtance, they muſt needes be tranſcribed. As if divers men, building on the ſame founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, guided by the ſame Spirit, may not in their Meditations border each on other, vnleſſe they bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row one from another.</p>
            <p>All theſe iuſt allegations were vrged by mee, but in vaine; I did but <hi>ſurdo narrare fabulam,</hi> my friends would haue no nay; for their ſakes haue I ventred to put my finger once againe into the fire, though already ſcorched with the ſlame. Happily the ſubiect matter of this Diſcourſe will procure better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainement.</p>
            <p>Many, I confeſſe, haue written of this <hi>Theame,</hi> and as our <hi>Adverſaries</hi> querulouſly complaine, too many. Wherefore els doe they ſay, What? nothing but the <hi>Powder-Treaſon?</hi> nothing but the <hi>Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-Treaſon?</hi> When will you haue done with your <hi>Cole-worts,</hi> twice thrice ſodden over. It vexeth them to the Heart, that wee ſhould rubbe this Soare, and make this wound bleed afreſh, but by their
<pb facs="tcp:4221:5"/> leaues, <hi>GODS goodneſſe,</hi> and <hi>Their wickedneſſe</hi> deſerues a <hi>Monument</hi> of <hi>Marble,</hi> and let them haue it. They loue the Treaſon, but hate the Memory of it.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Iſtis ſiquidem pudor eſt audiendi quae ſecerunt,</l>
               <l>Nullus faciendi quae erubeſcant.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Let all Ages ring of this tranſcendent match-leſſe mercileſſe <hi>Plot.</hi> Let every true-hearted <hi>Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> tell what great Wonders the Lord hath done for this <hi>Nation,</hi> how Hee carried our Fathers in the <hi>yeare Eightie-Eight through the waters:</hi> how Hee carried vs their children <hi>this fifth of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember through the fire.</hi> Let this be graven with a <hi>Penne</hi> of <hi>Iron,</hi> with the <hi>Point of a Diamond,</hi> on the Tables of our hearts, on the Poſtes of our Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, on the Hornes of our Altars, in ſuch Capitall Letters, as he that runnes may reade them. Let the Fathers report it to their children, and the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to their childrens children, that the Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to come, as yet vnborne, may diſcerne the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious miſchievous attempts of <hi>Romane Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Law of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, let it not here take place; but by tradition let it ſucceſsiuely deſcend from hand to hand, from mouth to mouth, from penn to penn, leaſt in time, <hi>Hiſtories, Chronicles,</hi> all <hi>Narrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:4221:6"/> hereof, ſeeme to after-Ages incredible, and this Truth bee entertained for a Fable, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede exceeds all Heathen <hi>Poeticall Fictions</hi> as farre as they exceed the <hi>Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Their Tenet is, that the <hi>Bread</hi> is tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> into the body of Chriſt.</note>No marvaile if they who craſh their <hi>Saviour</hi> betweene their teeth, make no bones to cruſh their <hi>Soveraigne.</hi> No marvaile if thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>GOD-eaters,</hi> (that make and bake their GOD, and champe him when they haue done) prooue <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>MAN-eaters</hi> (worſe then <hi>Canni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals</hi>) <hi>STATE-devourers.</hi> What may they not doe to advance the <hi>Catholike Cauſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not need to aggravate their Crueltie, Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherie, their owne <hi>Acts</hi> proclaime it to the World. Store of this <hi>Coyne</hi> is dayly Minted at <hi>ROME.</hi> New proiects are daily forged on the <hi>Anvills</hi> of the <hi>Ieſuites braines:</hi> So iuſt is it with GOD to giue them over, that their owne tongues and handes, ſhould be the chiefe Heralds to blazon the barbarous and ſavage diſpoſition of theſe Blood-ſuckers to the whole World.</p>
            <p>Thus doe they paint themſelues in ſuch <hi>Orient co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours,</hi> that no <hi>Oratour</hi> can more liuely ſet them out, whoſe <hi>Mercy</hi> is <hi>Crueltie; Pietie, Butchery; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Vide</hi> Acts of Parliam.</p>
                  <p>Witneſſe <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi> and others, who being iuſtly execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> are Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonized for Saints at <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> 
               <hi>Faction; Devotion, Sedition:</hi> whoſe <hi>Zeale</hi> is <hi>Fire; Prayers, Powder; Teares, Death; Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, Traytors; Saints, Devils Incarnate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But my lines ſwell, I muſt breake off, though ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptly, leaſt the garment proue too wide for the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die; leaſt the Preamble exceed the Treatiſe; Iudge</p>
            <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4221:6"/>
            <head>THE TRIVMPH OF THE CHVRCH OVER <hi>FIRE</hi> AND <hi>WATER.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ISAIAH 43.2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>When thou paſſeſt through the <hi>Waters</hi> I will be with thee, and through the Rivers they ſhall not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow thee; When thou walkeſt through the <hi>Fire</hi> thou ſhalt not be burnt; neither ſhall the <hi>flame kindle</hi> vpon thee.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this Chapter wee receiue ſome Sermon-notes; the Preacher was <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> the Hearers, the Inhabitants of <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> The Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon is worthy ſuch a Teacher; for deſcent, of the blood-royall; for Oratory, he goes beyond all the Prophets of his
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:4221:7"/> time, in elegancy of ſtile. His diſcourſe begins (as learned <hi>Iunius</hi> obſerues) at the two and fortieth Chapter, and reaches to the foureteene Verſe of this Chapter, which howſoever vniuſtly out and diſmembred from the former, muſt be redintigra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and added to the precedent Chapter, to make vp a full and entire diſcourſe. The maine paſſages of his ſpeech may be reduced to three Heads.</p>
            <list>
               <item>A Propheticall Prediction.</item>
               <item>A ſharpe Reprehenſion.</item>
               <item>A ſweete Conſolation.</item>
            </list>
            <p>In his Prediction this Evangelicall Prophet, and Propheticall Evangeliſt, (not vnworthily ſo ſtiled by ſome of the Antients) as having the Honor of all that ever went before him in his cleare Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, (ſeeming rather <hi>Hiſtories</hi> of what was already paſt, then <hi>Propheſies</hi> of ſuch things which after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Centuries of yeares were to be accompliſhed,) giues a liuely and excellent deſcription of the <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias,</hi> from the laſt Verſe of the fortie-two Chapter to the ſeaventeenth of this Chapter.</p>
            <p n="1">1. His <hi>Qualification</hi> in the adminiſtration of his office, Verſes 1.2.3.4.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His <hi>Commiſsion</hi> to warrant the execution of his office, grounded on the vocation of his father, from the fifth to the ninth verſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>reciprocall office</hi> of the Church towards Chriſt, breaking forth into Songs and Hymnes of prayſe and thankſ-giuing, verſes 10.11.12.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>effect of all,</hi> in reſpect of the Church and the enemies of the Church; which are layd downe <hi>inner ſo ordine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The laſt firſt.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Touching his enemies;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:4221:7"/> their Confuſion is threatned in a high Rhetoricall ſtraine, verſ. 13.14.15. Touching the Church; her Converſion is promiſed in a Metaphoricall alluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, verſ. 16.17.18. Then he fals very appoſitly by way of interrogation into a ſharpe <hi>Commination</hi> (his ſecond maine paſſge) laying downe the <hi>ſinne</hi> firſt, the blindneſſe and heedleſneſſe of thoſe careleſſe and ſecure both Prieſts and people, who profited nought, neither by the mercies nor iudgements of the Lord, ver. 19.20.21. The <hi>iudgements</hi> next; which (for the further aggravation of their ſinne and puniſhment) are amplified firſt from the <hi>Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> of them, in many phraſes very Emphaticall, they were <hi>robbed, ſpoyled, ſnared, made a prey,</hi> verſ. 22. <hi>the wrath of God poured vpon them, like water, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed them like fire,</hi> verſ. 25. Secondly, from their ſenſeleſſe ſtupiditie; they could not reade the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation of God in thoſe deſolations; ſo much is intimated in the queſtion propounded, verſ. 24. Who <hi>gaue Iacob to a ſpoyle?</hi> So much is expreſſed in the reaſon annexed, verſ. 25. <hi>He ſet him on fire round about, yet he knew it not, and it burned him, yet he layd it not to heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now leaſt the children of God ſhould be diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged and frighted too much, with thoſe blowes that were dealt ſo thicke among the wicked, hee haſtens with all ſpeede to ſtrengthen the heart of the righteous, and reacheth them this <hi>Cordiall</hi> to reviue their drooping ſpirits. But <hi>now, ſayth the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. The Prophet to approue himſelf a wiſe workeman giueth <hi>mercy to whom mercy;</hi> iudgement to whom <hi>iudgement belongs:</hi> and as hee had ſhewed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:4221:8"/> himſelfe a right <hi>Bonoarges</hi> a Sonne of thunder, ſo now hee will approue himſelfe a true <hi>Barnabas</hi> a Sonne of conſolation. He was not ſo terrible in his <hi>Commination,</hi> but hee will be as ſweete in his <hi>Conſolation.</hi> This Conſolation is deliuered by way of Iniunction <hi>feare not.</hi> Then the reaſon is annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or certaine grounds propounded why we <hi>ſhould not feare,</hi> from <hi>verſe</hi> the 2. to the 14. <hi>verſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>The reaſons are drawne partly from
<list>
                     <item>The Nature of God,</item>
                     <item>His Workes.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>From his <hi>Nature;</hi> he is <hi>Iehovah,</hi> conſtant to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, euer as good as his word.</p>
            <list>
               <item>From his workes
<list>
                     <item>Paſt,</item>
                     <item>Future.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Paſt</hi> he inſtances in three great and grand workes of
<list>
                     <item>Creation.</item>
                     <item>Redemption.</item>
                     <item>Vocation.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Future,</hi> of Direction, he would guide them through the Water.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Future,</hi> of Protection, he would guard them in the Fire.</item>
            </list>
            <p>All this Summarily propounded in the firſt and ſecond verſes. The Iniunction, or inhibition is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated <hi>v.</hi> 5. The Arguments of confirmation they alſo are againe and againe vrged by former experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and proofes of the power, providence, and goodnes of God: <hi>v.</hi> 3.4.5.6.7. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Notable it is to conſider how theſe <hi>promiſes</hi> are preſſed, iterated, inculcated: ſuch is the diffidence of our nature that in our extreamities wee are apt to reiect all comfort, and therefore the Lord by his Prophet labours to <hi>force</hi> them on vs. I haue dwelt too long in the confines, and borders, now let vs draw neare to the body of my Text; Conſider brie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fly the <hi>ſcope and parts</hi> of it.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:4221:8"/>
            <p>Theſe wordes carry in them a <hi>promiſe of Protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> an engagement royall, where in the Great <hi>Lord of Lords, King of Kings, the High &amp; Mighty, Monarch</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> giues a ſafe convoye to his <hi>Spouſe</hi> paſſing through the <hi>Arabian deſert,</hi> the vaſt and roaring <hi>wildernes</hi> of this world, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all oppoſitions and encounters of <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>water,</hi> he would ſet her ſafe in the <hi>Heavenly Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan.</hi> This is the ſum. The parts into which the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence naturally breakes it ſelfe, as the principall branches are two. Behold here, the <hi>wraſtling of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob;</hi> the <hi>Conqueſt of Iacob</hi> after his wraſtling: behold the <hi>Affliction of Ioſeph;</hi> the <hi>evaſion of Ioſeph</hi> out of his affliction: behold, the <hi>troubles of the Saints,</hi> the <hi>Triumph of the Saints</hi> after thoſe troubles: Behold, the <hi>Dangers of the Church;</hi> her <hi>Deliverance</hi> and reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cue from thoſe Dangers.
<list>
                  <item>In the wraſtling note the certainty of thoſe</item>
                  <item>In the wraſtling note the variety of thoſe</item>
                  <item>In the wraſtling note the extremity of thoſe</item>
               </list> afflictions with which the <hi>Iſrael of God</hi> doe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter. Their <hi>certainty</hi> in that he muſt paſſe through <hi>fire and water;</hi> the <hi>variety,</hi> in that he muſt paſſe not through <hi>water</hi> onely, but <hi>fire</hi> too, not through <hi>fire</hi> onely, but <hi>water</hi> too; vnder both all ſorts and kindes of affliction are compriſed.</p>
            <p>The extremity; fire &amp; water <hi>are thoſe mercileſſe ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts,</hi> yet they muſt not paſſe by theſe, by the <hi>fire,</hi> by the <hi>water,</hi> but <hi>through</hi> the fire, &amp; <hi>through</hi> the water; what greater danger then (as we ſay) to run <hi>through fire and water?</hi> Neither is here <hi>water</hi> mentioned onely, but <hi>flouds</hi> or rivers of water, nor <hi>fire</hi> onely,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4221:9"/> but a <hi>flame</hi> too, ſo the words of the Text carry it; <hi>When thou paſſeſt through, &amp;c.</hi> The Triumph fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, where we may obſerue
<list>
                  <item>The victory acquired. <hi>The flouds, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Author to whom the glory of this vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory muſt be aſcribed, <hi>I will be with thee. Therefore the flouds ſhall not over-flow thee, the flame ſhall not kindle vpon thee.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Thus by way of reſolution haue wee taken this frame aſunder, now let vs view the ſeverall parts, and then ſet it together ioynt by ioynt. We will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with the connexion, which I cannot paſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, ſeeing it affoords an excellent inſtruction; <hi>Gods former mercies are pledges of his future favours:</hi> by what he hath done, he ſhewes vs what he will doe: whom he hath created, whom he hath redeemed, whom he hath called, (they may build on it) they ſhall be preſerued, protected. Thus it holds vſually in temporall mercies; the bleſſings of God never goe ſingle: wee cannot ſay to the Lord as <hi>Eſau</hi> to <hi>Iſaac,</hi> haſt thou <hi>but one bleſsing my father,</hi> but rather (as <hi>Leah</hi> of <hi>Gad</hi>) <hi>a troupe cometh.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 39.11.</note> The ſtory obſerues how he bleſſed <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in his fathers houſe, in his Maſters houſe, in the priſon-houſe, in his owne houſe, when a ſlaue, when a Lord, in the ſtockes, on the throne,<note place="margin">Gen. 30.42.</note> where ever he goeth, what euer he doth, ſtill <hi>Ioſeph</hi> proſpers. See it in <hi>Iacob;</hi> though <hi>Laban</hi> change his wages ten times, yet the weakeſt ſheepe goe to <hi>Laban,</hi> the ſtrongeſt fall to <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſhare. See it in <hi>Abram,</hi> in <hi>Lot:</hi> the Lord reueales himſelfe to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bram,</hi> doth that for <hi>Abram,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 12.1.</note> as he had not done for any perſon or Nation. Is that all? No, hee bleſſeth
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4221:9"/> him as in his Soule, ſo in his eſtate too:<note place="margin">Gen. 13.2.9.</note> 
               <hi>Abram</hi> growes exceeding rich, <hi>Lot</hi> and he their wealth parts them, one Country cannot hold them: But this holds eſpecially, and infallibly, in ſpirituall mercies, one bleſſing here euer drawes on another, ſo chained they are, and linked together, as one ſtill treads on the heele of another, the leſſer makes way for the greater. Take one famous inſtance, in ſtead of a thouſand. It is preſented by <hi>Paul,</hi> in that <hi>Golden</hi> chaine with the linkes of it knit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29.30. <hi>Thoſe which he knew before, he alſo predeſtinated, moreouer thoſe whom he predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them alſo hee called, whom hee called, them alſo hee iuſtified, and whom he iuſtified, them alſo he glorified,</hi> Loe here is that <hi>Adamantine chaine,</hi> one linke ſo faſtened to another, that Hell-gates cannot ſunder them. So <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.6. the ſame Apoſtle perſwades himſelfe, that he that <hi>had begun that good worke in them, would finiſh it;</hi> to one fauour of <hi>Inchoation,</hi> he will adde the other of <hi>Conſummation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſtrength of this diduction was notably em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued by <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> both.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 17.34.35.36.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> reaſons thus, he that reſcued him from the <hi>claw of the Lyon, and the paw of the beare,</hi> would not leaue him as a prey in the hand of that vncircumciſed <hi>Philiſtim. Paul</hi> thus, <hi>he hath delivered vs, he doth deliver vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>in whom I truſt he will deliver vs;</hi> if this will carry force in temporall,<note place="margin">From the Greater.</note> it holds <hi>à Maiori</hi> in ſpirituall caſes; as in privatiue, ſo in poſitiue bleſſings.</p>
            <p>The reaſons hereof may be drawne, partly from the <hi>bounty,</hi> partly from the <hi>Immutabilitie</hi> of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie. His bountie is ſuch, that where he begins
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4221:10"/> (I will not ſay he knowes not) ſure I am he cannot or at leaſt he will not make an end. Firſt he creates them, then redeemes them, then cals them, then protects them; and yet comes not to a <hi>full period.</hi> The Lord is no <hi>niggard</hi> in beſtowing his favours, but liberall and franke. His Bounty like a perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>Spring,</hi> runs continually, over-flowes all bankes. He giues exceeding abundantly <hi>aboue all that wee are able to aske or thinke:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.20.</note> obſerving <note n="*" place="margin">His Meaſure is without meaſure.</note> 
               <hi>Modum ſine Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond ground is his <hi>Immutabilitie,</hi> whether of his <hi>Nature</hi> or <hi>Decree.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 3.14.</note> In regard of his <hi>Nature,</hi> he is ever <hi>(I am):</hi> if mercifull in former times, he is as mercifull for the preſent, and will be for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.17. He <hi>is without variableneſs or ſhadow of change.</hi> His Decree is as vnchangeable as his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. His promiſes, his purpoſes are not vnſtable, <hi>yea and nay,</hi> but <hi>yea and Amen; yeſterday, to day, the ſame for ever.</hi> 2 Cor. 1.10. He doth not loue one day, hate the next: Bleſſe one day, curſe the next; aſſiſt this day, forſake the next.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> A notable ſtaffe to vnderprop our faith. He will be <hi>Iehovah</hi> (<hi>Exod</hi> 34.6.7.) ever the ſame conſtant to himſelfe and his ſervants. Remember the dayes that are paſt, looke backe to the times of old: hath he beene the God of thy fathers, he will be thy God alſo,<note place="margin">Gen. 13.15.17.7.</note> (the promiſe is made to them and their ſeed) hath he delivered their fore-fathers, he will not flinch from their children, if they degenerate not, but tread in their fathers ſteppes.</p>
            <p>Let vs apply this to our ſelues firſt in particular; to our Nation next in generall. Hath hee created
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4221:10"/> thee? hath he redeemed thee? hath hee adopted thee? he will deliuer thee, he will ſanctifie thee, he will glorifie thee. Treaſure vp experiences of fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed fauours, it will keepe thy head aboue water from ſinking in preſent euills: needes muſt that Man ſwimme, which is held vp by the chinne; that Soule cannot ſtagger which is vnderpropped by ſuch preſidents and patternes, I may not dwell in ſpecials, this reacheth to our whole <hi>Nation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Good the more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon, the more Good.</note> 
               <hi>Bonum quo communius eo melius.</hi> Neuer any people enioyed more and greater teſtimonies of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, why may not we exſpect the continuance of his loue? He hath created vs after his owne Image, redeemed vs from the <hi>ſlauery of ſinne,</hi> from that worſe then <hi>Egyptian bondage,</hi> from the <hi>yoake</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>tyranny of Antichriſt;</hi> he hath <hi>called vs by name,</hi> entred into couenant with vs, ſtriken a firme League; Hee hath taken vs for his people;<note place="margin">Hoſca. 1.10.</note> wee chalenge him for our God. Let vs but keepe to him, he will not ſtart from vs. Let the Church of God euer magnifie the riches of his ſuper abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant grace that <hi>ladeth</hi> vs with his <hi>bleſsings,</hi> and not onely <hi>cheriſheth</hi> vs with the remembrance of old fauours, but doubles the Benefits, by giuing them as <hi>pledges</hi> of future and greater. As the firſt fruites promiſed a plentifull crop, and as the earneſt (though ſmall) aſſureth vs of the whole bargaine: ſo the leaſt mercy is great in this, that it is but the <hi>firſt fruites,</hi> but a beginning, but an earneſt, a pledge of more and greater. Thus may we in generall, in particular, if the fault be not our owne, from that wee haue already receiued, promiſe to our ſelues farre greater matters for the time to come. But
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:4221:11"/> what doe I ſtaying ſo long in the <hi>ſkirtes,</hi> let vs now as <hi>Moſes</hi> aſcended Mount <hi>Nebo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 32.4.</note> ſo climbe this Mount in my Text, and there take a double proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect: firſt we may looke backward, and there view the <hi>Iſrael of God</hi> now paſſing through the <hi>Red Sea,</hi> now ſtung with fiery Serpents in the wildernes of this World: wee may then looke forward and ſee them victorious ouer <hi>fire and water,</hi> in their heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Canaan,</hi> like their Lord and Maſter, as here crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with thornes, ſo there crowned with victory and glory. It ſeemes good to their heauenly Father, to entertaine them wit <hi>ſtormes</hi> firſt, and after they haue runne ſome dangerous hazards, to bring a gracious <hi>calme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>affliction of Ioſeph,</hi> is not nakedly propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but notably amplyfied, from <hi>the certainty, the variety, the extremity of it.</hi> The certainty is inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated, this the Lord takes for granted, that his <hi>Spouſe</hi> muſt through <hi>fire and water. When thou paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt &amp;c.</hi> As if the Lord had expreſſed his minde in other tearmes. Miſtake me not, I neuer enten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to ſecure my choſen wholy from danger, or to ſet them out of the reach of affliction; that the <hi>water</hi> ſhould not touch them, nor they touch the <hi>water;</hi> at the <hi>fire</hi> ſhould not come neare them, nor they come neare the <hi>fire;</hi> but to get my ſelfe a name and glory, to magnifie my power and pitty, by ſecuring them in the water, that the <hi>flouds</hi> ſhall not <hi>over-flow them,</hi> by ſecuring them in the <hi>fire</hi> that the <hi>flame</hi> ſhall not <hi>kindle</hi> vpon them. The Saintes muſt haue their <hi>Purgatory on earth,</hi> that of <hi>water to waſh</hi> off the filth and ſoile contracted by ſinne; that other of <hi>fire to purge</hi> out the droſſe of corruption.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:4221:11"/> The Concluſion ſtandes as firme as Heaven and Earth.</p>
            <p>The Church Militant, while ſhee remaines in this vaile of teares, and valley of miſery, is not priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from miſeries and calamities. Let her be the <hi>Darling of Heaven,</hi> the <hi>favorite of the great King,</hi> the worke of his hand, his Redeemed, his adopted, his Beloved one, no bonds, no entirenes with God can plead an <hi>exemption.</hi> Shee is the Lords Shippe, his <hi>Marchant-royall,</hi> and therefore muſt expect ſtormes while ſhee Sailes on the tempeſtuous <hi>Sea</hi> of this world. His <hi>Lilly,</hi> and therefore muſt grow in the midſt of <hi>thornes;</hi> his <hi>Roſe,</hi> and therefore muſt be enuironed with prickles; his <hi>Gold,</hi> and therefore muſt be caſt ever and anon into the fiery furnace; his <hi>Campe-royall,</hi> and therefore muſt be ever skirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing; his <hi>vine,</hi> and therefore ever and anon muſt be pruned. This is the place of her <hi>Labour,</hi> no reſt from her labour, till her worke be at an end; no end of her worke, till an end be put to theſe dayes of ſinne. <hi>Bleſſed are they that die in the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 14.13.</note> 
               <hi>for they ſhall reſt from their labours.</hi> So much was ſhadowed out and typified by the Riding of <hi>Noahs Arke</hi> on the Waters; by the <hi>ſmoaking fire-brands,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 7.17. Gen. 15.17.</note> preſented to <hi>Abram;</hi> by the <hi>wraſtling</hi> of <hi>Iacob;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen 32.24. Exod. 3.2.</note> by the <hi>Burning Buſh,</hi> preſented to <hi>Moſes:</hi> ſo much is plainly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by our Saviour; <hi>In the world you ſhall haue trouble.</hi> Ioh. 16.33. <hi>He that will be my Diſciple, muſt take vp his croſſe and follow we.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ground hereof may be drawne, partly from the appointment of God, partly from the malice of Satan; partly from that correſpondence which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:4221:12"/> ſhould ever be maintained betweene the <hi>Head</hi> and the <hi>Members.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, It is that <hi>Decree</hi> enacted by the <hi>High Court of Parliament in Heaven,</hi> a Statute more firme then the Lawes of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> that the way to Heaven ſhall be <hi>ſtrawed</hi> with <hi>croſſes;</hi> that <hi>every one that will liue godly in Chriſt Ieſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall ſuffer perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> This is that <hi>thorny path</hi> which is chalked out as the <hi>common Rhode,</hi> leading to Glory. No man muſt expect two <hi>Heavens,</hi> one here, another hereafter. Would you know the ground of this Sanction? though his <hi>Will be a Law,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sic volo, ſic iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beo; ſtet pro ratione volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas. <hi>Eccleſ. 8.4.</hi>
               </note> though it be a ſaucineſſe to ſay to the <hi>King (much more to the King of Kinges) What doeſt thou?</hi> Yet ſith the wiſe God is pleaſed to condeſcend ſo farre vnto our weakenes, as to yeeld an account of his actions, know it tends much to his <hi>glory,</hi> and the <hi>good</hi> of the Saints. It tends to the <hi>Glory of his wiſedome,</hi> that fetcheth <hi>light</hi> out of <hi>dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, life</hi> out of <hi>death, Heaven</hi> out of <hi>Hell;</hi> to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his <hi>power,</hi> that brings <hi>ſtrength</hi> out of <hi>weaknes.</hi> So the <hi>Oracle</hi> to <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.9.</note> 
               <hi>My grace is ſufficient for thee. My power is made perfect through weakneſſe.</hi> It turnes to the good of the Saints, who <hi>are corrected with his children, that they might not be condemned with the world.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 3.12. Heb. 12.6. Revel. 3.19. Prov. 22.15.</note> 
               <hi>Whom the Lord loues he chaſtens. There is much folly bound in the heart of the childe</hi> (as that <hi>Mirror of wiſedom</hi> giues out in his ſelect divine Aphoriſmes) <hi>but the rod of correction will fetch it out. Bleſſed is the Man whom thou chaſtiſeſt</hi> (O Lord) <hi>and teacheſt thy Law,</hi> ſo <hi>David</hi> the Father of ſo wiſe a Sonne. Theſe <hi>Nocumenta</hi> are <hi>Documenta,</hi> his Corrections are In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions. Wee ſee by experience theſe <hi>Starres</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:4221:12"/> ſhine brighteſt in the darkeſt night; theſe <hi>ſheepe</hi> thriue beſt in the <hi>ſalteſt Marſhes,</hi> and tread ſureſt in the <hi>rougheſt way;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſoveraign Salue for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Soare.</note> theſe <hi>Diamonds</hi> glitter moſt in the night; this <hi>corne</hi> is pureſt from <hi>chaffe</hi> when vnder the <hi>ſtaile:</hi> theſe <hi>torches</hi> blaze moſt when they are moſt beaten. <hi>Abrams faith, Iobs patience, Davids Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, Salomons Recantation, Manaſſehs humiliation,</hi> all theſe, with thouſand more, giue evident demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, that the graces of the Spirit (like the <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bian Spices</hi>) never yeeld a more <hi>fragrant ſmell</hi> then when they are punned and bruzed together in the <hi>Morter of Affliction.</hi> This is the firſt reaſon, God hath appointed it, and that for his <hi>glory</hi> and our <hi>good. Deus enim adeo bonus eſt, vt nihil mali ſineret, niſi etiam adeo eſſet potens, vt ex quolibet malo poſsit elicere bonum.</hi> Thus <hi>Auſtin,</hi> Such is the <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> of God, that he would permit no <hi>euill,</hi> vnleſſe he knew his <hi>Power</hi> to be ſuch, as he could draw <hi>good</hi> out of <hi>euill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Adde to this (in the ſecond place) the envy of <hi>Satan</hi> and his Inſtruments. The Devill will at leaſt make vs haue a wet <hi>ſeede-time,</hi> if he cannot hinder our <hi>ioyfull harveſt;</hi> he will be ſure to make vs liue diſcomfortably in earth, if he cannot hinder vs from raigning gloriouſly in Heaven; he will <hi>bruiſe our heele, if he cannot breake our head.</hi> His inſtruments carried with the ſpleene of their father the Devill, will <hi>trouble</hi> vs, though they cannot <hi>hurt</hi> vs, with <hi>Midianitiſh</hi> wiles, they will vexe the <hi>Iſrael of GOD,</hi> whom they cannot Conquer: theſe ſnarling, bau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Curres will barke and ſnatch at the <hi>Moone,</hi> though they cannot ſtay her courſe. If wee doe but ſet our faces towardes <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> if wee but ſteale a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:4221:13"/> looke to <hi>Heaven</hi>-ward, theſe <hi>Samaritans</hi> will be ſtraight on our backes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 5.7.8.</note>The laſt Reaſon ſtands with <hi>equitie,</hi> that wee might be made conformable to our High-Prieſt, who <hi>was conſecrated by afflictions.</hi> The <hi>Head</hi> was a <hi>Man of ſorrow,</hi> and ſhall the <hi>body</hi> know no ſorrow? The <hi>head</hi> was crowned with <hi>thornes,</hi> and all goare blood <hi>(tota cicatrix)</hi> ſhall the <hi>body</hi> be <hi>decked with Roſes?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 13:16.</note> Shall the ſervant looke to fare better then his maſter;<note place="margin">Luk. 24.26.</note> 
               <hi>if they called me Beel-zebub, how much more thoſe of my family,</hi> as the Lord fore-warnes his Diſciples. If that hold, <hi>Opertet Chriſtum pati,</hi> then much more, <hi>Oportet Chriſtianum pati,</hi> ſo one of the <hi>Ancients.</hi> Muſt Chriſt ſuffer? is there not the ſame Muſt, for euery Chriſtian? Whence another of the Fathers deſcants on the name, <hi>Chriſtianus quaſi Crucianus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Let this checke thoſe fond Chriſtians, whether lazy Proteſtants, or ignorant Papiſts; the former wiſh it were, the latter affirme it, that eaſe, peace, calmes, and faire-weather, are the markes and bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of a true Church; which they ſet out of the reach of perſecution, which they make to be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with a perpetuated ſucceſſion of an vninterrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted peace, plentie, and tranquilitie; as if they one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (contrary to the ordinary courſe) muſt be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to heaven on a feather-bed; as if it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to ſaile through the <hi>tempeſtuous Seas</hi> of this world, and never meete with a <hi>ſtorme;</hi> as if all <hi>croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> to them were turned into <hi>roſes</hi> and <hi>ruſhes;</hi> as if the <hi>ſervant</hi> ſhould be more cockered then the <hi>Son: Auſtin</hi> put this out of doubt, <hi>Vnicum filium habuit
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4221:13"/> ſine peccato, neminem habuit ſine flagello.</hi> God had <hi>one Sonne that knew no ſinne, never any that felt no ſmart.</hi> What is, if this be not repugnant to the plain Text, and ſtrong current of holy Writ? Which propheſies not of <hi>peace</hi> but of <hi>warre,</hi> not of <hi>ſecuritie</hi> but of <hi>calamitie;</hi> not of ſleeping in a whole <hi>skinne,</hi> but of bearing in our bodies the <hi>wounds</hi> or the <hi>Lord Ieſus,</hi> not of a ſmooth gale, but of many croſſe, nay, adverſe blaſts. It is given a note rather of that Whore of <hi>Babylon, to ſit as a Queene, a Lady,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel. 18.7.</note> having her mountaine ſo ſtrongly founded, ſo rarely aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted, that ſhee never dreames of a change, <hi>When the Daughters of Sion; hang their Harpes vpon the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, and ſit weeping at the waters of Babel:</hi> It is for <hi>Moab</hi> rather to be <hi>ſetled on her lees,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere. 48.11.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe ſhee is not ſhaken from veſſell to veſſell:</hi> When the <hi>Iſrael of God</hi> are toſſed from poſt to pillar:<note place="margin">Pſal. 129.1.2.</note> 
               <hi>from my youth vp haue they afflicted me, will Iſrael ſay from my youth vp, &amp;c.</hi> It is for the <hi>Generation</hi> of <hi>Eſau</hi> to carry the world before them in a continued line of ſucceſſion, <hi>Duke</hi> vpon <hi>Duke.</hi> Twelue <hi>Dukes</hi> were found in <hi>Edom,</hi> when the children of <hi>Iacob</hi> were labouring at the Brick-kils in <hi>Egypt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 12.19.20.</note> It is for the <hi>foole</hi> in the Goſpel to ſing a lullaby to his Soule, <hi>Soule take thine eaſe, &amp;c.</hi> Who had his <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> his <hi>Conſolation</hi> here. Wee that expect that <hi>Glory to come,</hi> muſt not looke for an <hi>Heaven vpon earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Let this leſſon thoſe holy Ones what to expect in this world, even that which they haue ever found, <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>water.</hi> Oppoſitions, troubles, and perſecutions. God will allow no peace to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, the wicked will afford no peace to the godly.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:4221:14"/> In the midſt of our diſcomforts, let this be our comfort, it is the common Lot of the Saints, why ſhould we ſhrug at it? When ſo many haue broken the ice before vs; ſince it is no new thing; why ſhould we thinke it a ſtrange thing to heare or feele the <hi>fiery tryalls?</hi> Since it is the will of God, <hi>beare</hi> it patiently, ſince it makes for the <hi>Glory</hi> of God, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in it exceedingly; ſith the <hi>Good</hi> will be our owne, take it thankefully; ſo ſhall your <hi>Croſſe</hi> bee your <hi>Crowne,</hi> ſo ſhall you be as glorious in your greateſt miſery, as the wicked are miſerable in their greateſt glory.</p>
            <p>I haue done now with the <hi>Afflictions of Ioſeph;</hi> and yet I haue not done neither; giue me leaue to recall my ſelfe, the Spirit puls me backe, this is not all. The <hi>Spouſe</hi> is not ſubject to affliction onely, <hi>(this is but the beginning of ſorrow)</hi> but to <hi>many and great afflictions. Many</hi> for <hi>varietie; great</hi> for <hi>extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie.</hi> Shee muſt through <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>water.</hi> Both theſe ſtreames runne into one and the ſame fountaine; the matter will be Co-incident, that wee may not <hi>enter fiere,</hi> let vs wrappe both in one, and giue you the Doctrine in the words of the <hi>Kingly Prophet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Many are the Troubles of the righteous;</hi> that is, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and great, <hi>Multa &amp;c magna,</hi> ſo much the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall word doth intimate. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.19. For their number <hi>many;</hi> for their meaſure <hi>great;</hi> for their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>weightie.</hi> Take the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> firſt, that it is ſo, and then the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, why it is ſo, as they ſpeake in the Schooles.</p>
            <p>To begin with my Text, here is not <hi>fire</hi> onely, but <hi>water</hi> too, not <hi>water</hi> onely, but <hi>fire</hi> too: <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:4221:14"/> comprehend all ſorts of tryals; there is <hi>the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie.</hi> Againe, here is fire and water; thoſe two mercileſſe Elements, <hi>(good ſervants, but cruell Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters)</hi> which comprehends the greateſt danger, the extremeſt miſery that can befall a man. When the tender Father in the Goſpell (ſeeking the cure of his poſſeſſed ſonne) would ſtirre vp the bowels of our Saviour to commiſerate the diſtreſſed <hi>Daemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niaks,</hi> how doth he paynt out the crueltie and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of the Devill? delivers it to the full in theſe emphaticall termes; Loe,<note place="margin">Mat. 17.15,</note> 
               <hi>He caſts him ſometime into the fire, ſometimes into the water,</hi> and not able to hold any longer, he burſts out into tears, <hi>Lord take pittie on my Sonne.</hi> Yet to adde to the heape of their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, here is not <hi>water</hi> mentioned onely, but <hi>waters, rivers, flouds</hi> of <hi>water;</hi> not <hi>fire</hi> onely, ſome few ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles, but <hi>flames</hi> of <hi>fire,</hi> there is <hi>the extremitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> anſwereth that complaint of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid.</hi> Pſal. 42.7. <hi>Abyſſus abyſſum invocat; one deepe calleth vpon another deepe.</hi> Here is a depth of miſery to note the <hi>extremitie;</hi> deepe and deepe, to note the <hi>varietie:</hi> neither was this to ſome one member that might fall into theſe quag-myres, but the whole Church makes her moane; <hi>Many a time baue they afflicted me from my youth, may Iſrael now ſay, many a time have they afflicted me from my youth vp.</hi> Pſal. 129.12. That choſen veſſell forewarnes the <hi>Antiechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> that <hi>through many tribulations, they muſt enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Kingdome of God.</hi> Act. 14.22. As for the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle himſelfe, he had his ſhare as deepe as any, <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils by Sea, perils by Land, &amp;c.</hi> Strange it is to ſee what varietie of troubles, what a world of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:4221:15"/> (as it were can Army of Pykes,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.4.11.13. 2 Cor. 4.9.13</note> or a thicket of thornes) <hi>Paul</hi> ran through. <hi>David,</hi> a <hi>Man after Gods owne heart,</hi> what troubles vnder-went he at home? What dangers abroad? What from his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies? What from his friends? What inward af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction? What outward perſecution? As a man borne to ſorrow, that ſcarſe ever came where tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilitie grew. So that <hi>Mirrour of patience Iob,</hi> how came his croſſes and loſſes thicke and three-fold, like ſhowers of haile-ſhot;<note place="margin">Iob. 1.14.15.</note> 
               <hi>Velut vndam vndam ſequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> as waue followes waue in the midſt of the Sea. <hi>Solomon</hi> (Proverb. 24.16.) tels vs they come by <hi>troupes,</hi> by <hi>ſeavens,</hi> a certaine number put for an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine; <hi>many come,</hi> that is, <hi>certaine;</hi> but <hi>how many,</hi> that is, <hi>vncertaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who can number the <hi>ſtarres of the skie?</hi> Who can number the <hi>drops of the water?</hi> Who can num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the <hi>ſparkles of the fire?</hi> Who can count the <hi>dust of Iacob?</hi> Or who can number the <hi>fourth part of the afflictions of Ioſeph?</hi> But it is their <hi>nature</hi> I muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt on rather then their <hi>number;</hi> did not <hi>Experience</hi> (the Miſtreſſe of fooles) ſaue me that labour.</p>
            <p>The deareſt children of God (as wee often finde and feele) are they not put to great extremities, to ſhrewd plunges, to deſperate pinches? What a ſtrait was the Church brought to, thinke you, when the <hi>Edomits</hi> cryed, <hi>Downe with it, downe with it, even to the ground?</hi> What ſhould I protract time to inſtance in perſons, in places? What meane theſe and the like phraſes; <hi>The plowers haue ploughed on my backe, they made long furrowes.</hi> Pſal. 129.3. And againe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.12. <hi>Thou haſt cauſed men to ride over our
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:4221:15"/> heads, wee went through fire and water;</hi> the ſame al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion which is here in my Text. This is that <hi>bread</hi> of affliction, that <hi>water</hi> of affliction; that <hi>gall</hi> and <hi>wormwood</hi> wherewith he feedes his; that <hi>Baptiſme</hi> which our Saviour foreſpeakes to the Sonnes of <hi>Zebedeus;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>Mat. 10.38.39.</p>
                  <p>Luk. 12.50.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>Yee ſhall drinke indeed of that cup that I ſhall drinke of, and be baptized with the baptiſme wherewith I ſhall be baptized.</hi> If you take it <hi>literally,</hi> was not <hi>Noah</hi> carried <hi>through the water?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 7.18. Exod. 1.22.</note> and the <hi>Hebrew babes</hi> did they not paſſe <hi>through the flouds?</hi> The three Children went they not <hi>through the fire,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 3.23.</note> howbeit the flame kindled not vpon them? Thoſe bleſſed <hi>Martyrs,</hi> how many thouſands were ſent vp to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>Elias</hi>-like in <hi>fiery Chariots?</hi> If you take it <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually,</hi> theſe <hi>waters</hi> had even entred into <hi>Davids</hi> ſoule, he was not <hi>drenched</hi> onely, but almoſt <hi>ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed</hi> vp of thoſe waues. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 69.1.2.<note place="margin">Iob. 16.13. Iob. 7.12.</note> 
               <hi>Iob</hi> complaines that the <hi>Lord had ſet him as a Butt;</hi> that the <hi>arrowes of the Almightie ſtucke ſtucke faſt in his ribbes, the venom whereof had drunke vp his bloud;</hi> he was <hi>hedged in as a Whale. Ionah</hi> cryes from the bottome of the <hi>Whale, from the belly Hell.</hi> Ionah. 2.3.4.5.</p>
            <p>More <hi>Generall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 4.8.</note> when holy <hi>Abel</hi> lay bleeding vnder the bloudy knife of his butcherly brother <hi>Caine,</hi> was not the Church at a deſperate pinch? When <hi>Iſaac</hi> lay bound on the <hi>Altar, Abrahams</hi> hand now ſtretched out, and vp ready to giue the <hi>fatall ſtroake,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen, 22.10,</note> was not the Church at the laſt caſt gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping for life? When the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> were preſſed, in a manner oppreſſed with that ſore intollerable <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian</hi> bondage, when forced to march through the midſt of that <hi>red Sea, (figuring the blood,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod 14.22.</note> 
               <hi>red Sea
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:4221:16"/> of perſecution, through which all the Iſrael of God muſt wade)</hi> when thoſe <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> Bandes, the <hi>Caldean ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> brake their bankes, and like a violent ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwelling <hi>torrent</hi> ſwept all before them as a generall inundation,<note place="margin">2. Kings 18.11.</note> was not Gods <hi>Ston</hi> in the middeſt of the waters? when the Roman Troups put all to the fire and the ſword, not leauing <hi>one ſtone vpon a ſtone,</hi> of that famous <hi>Citty and Temple,</hi> (the wonder of the world) not throwne downe: or rather in the times of thoſe ten <hi>fiery perſecutions,</hi> when <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezars Oven was heated ſeuen times hotter then ordinary,</hi> was not the <hi>Buſh all in a flame?</hi> was not <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> in the <hi>middeſt of the fire?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What might be there reaſon will ſome demand, that the troubles of the righteous ſhould be ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and great? the ſame in a manner with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. It fals out thus, partly in reſpect of God, partly in reſpect of their enemies; in reſpect of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues partly, not principally.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iehovah</hi> permits it, ordaines it, orders it. Why? the more and the greater their afflictions are, the more doth his mercy ſhine, the greater doth his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and power appeare in their deliuerance, in their reſcue. When <hi>Iſrael</hi> was euery way diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,<note place="margin">Exod. 14.12.12.</note> the ſea before them, the army of the Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans behinde them preſſing at their heeles, the high towring Mountaines hemming them in on all ſides; now will the Lord get him <hi>honor vpon Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh and all his hoaſt. Exod.</hi> 14.4. Now will the <hi>Lord of Hoaſtes march valiantly, and overthrow the horſe and the rider.</hi> When the people of God were ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered ouer the foure corners of the world: now for
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:4221:16"/> God to turne againe the <hi>captivitie of Iacob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſaiah 43.12.14.</note> as the <hi>ſtreame back-ward;</hi> to bring them home weeping with their faces toward <hi>Sion,</hi> this ſhall be to mee (ſayth the Lord) an <hi>euerlaſting name, ioy and honor,</hi> now he ſhewes him-ſelfe a God.</p>
            <p>The greater the ſtreame is, the skill of the <hi>Pilot</hi> if hee ſteere the ſhippe aright, appeares to be the greater; the more deſperate the diſeaſe is, the cure is the more glorious; this may be one ground, why the troubles of the righteous are many and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that the mighty and <hi>manifold wiſedome, power, goodnes of Iehovah,</hi> might ſhine out in their <hi>full glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> to the admiration of Men and Angels.</p>
            <p>Another reaſon followes, becauſe their enemies are many and great; Their malice <hi>great,</hi> their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty <hi>great,</hi> their power <hi>great,</hi> their ſedulity <hi>great,</hi> their cruelty <hi>great.</hi> Conſider their ſubtilty, the ſlie <hi>Midianites</hi> haue a thouſand wiles and wayes to vexe and beguile the plaine hearted downe-right <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> Conſider their malice; there is an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall enmity put by God himſelfe between the ſeede of the woman, and the ſeede of the Serpent, which how euer ſmothered ſometimes as it were in the aſhes, yet euer and anon is blowne vp by the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes of vnplacable malice,<note place="margin">Gen. 15.</note> and breakes forth into an open flame, ſo vnſatiable it is, that nothing but the heart-blood of the Lambe will content thoſe rauenous Woolues. Conſider their <hi>cruelty;</hi> as for <hi>craft,</hi> they are <hi>foxes,</hi> and for <hi>ſubtilty, Serpents:</hi> ſo for <hi>cruelty, roaring ramping Lions,</hi> that will leaue no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne be it neuer ſo barbarous vnattempted, but will proſecute it to the vtmoſt of their power. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:4221:17"/> their <hi>ſedulitie,</hi> as the Devill their Maſter him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe goes about continually, ſeeking whom hee may deuoure; ſo his Impes, they <hi>compaſſe Sea and Land to make a Proſelite of their owne, and to render him ten-ſold more the childe of the Devill.</hi> Their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies are many, their name is <hi>Legion;</hi> their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies are mighty,<note place="margin">Ephe, 6.12.</note> they fight with Principalities and Powers, which are in high places, no marueile if their troubles be many and mighty. Their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies are many and miſcheiuous, cruell and barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, needes muſt their tryals be many, their caſe grieuous, their eſtate dangerous.</p>
            <p>Finally they may thanke themſelues for it; their ſinnes are many, their ſinnes are mighty; many ſinnes cauſe many afflictions, mighty ſinnes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure mighty troubles. Lay not the blame then on <hi>Religion,</hi> but on thy <hi>Corruption.</hi> Gods deareſt chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren will venture on noiſome meate and hurtfull poiſon; they will drinke downe the very <hi>gall of Aſpes,</hi> they will be walking neare Hels mouth, their Father therefore takes them by the heeles and makes them belieue he will throw them in. They will bee dallying with the fire, no marueile if they be ſcorched with the flame; they will be running into the water, no marueile if they be drenched in the waues: they will be laying the Serpent in their boſome, no marueile if they be ſtung with that Scorpion. They defile them ſelues with groſſe ſins, and therefore muſt haue much waſhing; they take in the <hi>deadlieſt poiſon,</hi> and therefore muſt haue <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king</hi> Phyſicke: while coruption is ſo ſtrong, let them looke for it; many and mighty corruptions
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:4221:17"/> will procure many and mighty afflictions.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> The emprouement is made by the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.7. chap. 4.13.</note> 
               <hi>thinke it not ſtrange, concerning the fiery tryall,</hi> ſo <hi>Peter; Count it great ioy when you fall <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> into divers temptations,</hi> ſo <hi>Iames.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iames 1.2.</note> If wee paſſe vnder ſeuere ſharpe corrections, and be forced to drinke of <hi>gall and wormewood,</hi> this is no new thing. Thoſe whom hee loues moſt hee corrects moſt; and if wee feele not the rod at all,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.8.</note> well may we ſuſpect we are <hi>baſtards not children:</hi> when wee reade of <hi>the troubles of David,</hi> when we heare of <hi>the afflictions of Ioſeph,</hi> when we heare, or ſee, or reade of the calamities of our <hi>Brethren,</hi> let it not diſmay vs too much: What though the Churches in <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia,</hi> in the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> in the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> be now floating in the midſt of the water? What though in the midſt of the fire, in thee furnace? What if that fire which was <hi>kindled</hi> in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> which <hi>flamed in France,</hi> which hath <hi>burnt</hi> vp and deuoured the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latinate,</hi> ſome <hi>ſparkles</hi> thereof ſhould fly ouer-ſea? (<hi>quod omen Deus avertat,</hi> which God forbid) why ſhould they or we, thinke much to pledge our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, in that <hi>cup</hi> which he began to vs? hee dranke the very <hi>lees and dregges</hi> of that <hi>mixed wine,</hi> we doe but ſip and taſt the top of it. Let our troubles be neuer ſo many, <hi>Chriſts</hi> were more; neuer ſo great, <hi>Chriſts</hi> were greater. He went through the <hi>water,</hi> when he ſweat <hi>drops of blood;</hi> he went through the <hi>fire,</hi> when like that good <hi>Phoenix,</hi> he continued on the <hi>croſſe,</hi> fluttering his winges ouer the <hi>burning coales</hi> of his Fathers indignation, till by ſuffering the extremitie of it, he quenched that flame with
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:4221:18"/> his owne blood, which els had burnt to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of Hell.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> This ſecondly affoords Comfort, as to all the members of Chriſt in particular, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> are bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, whether <hi>Baptiſmo ſluminis,</hi> or <hi>baptiſmo ſlami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> with this Baptiſme of <hi>fire</hi> or <hi>water;</hi> ſo eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to theſe our <hi>Churches,</hi> and this our <hi>State</hi> of <hi>Great Britaine</hi> in Generall. If the mightie God of <hi>Iacob</hi> had not called vs by name, and given to this <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph that parti-coloured</hi> coate <hi>(the livery of his loue)</hi> the <hi>Covenant of grace,</hi> wee ſhould neuer haue beene ſo maligned by Satan, ſo hated of the world, ſo perſecuted by Sea and Land, ſo driven through <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>water;</hi> wee ſhould never haue beene hated ſo mortally, handled ſo cruelly, butchered ſo bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barouſly, plotted againſt ſo divelliſhly: If any Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vnder the <hi>Cope</hi> of <hi>Heauen</hi> can apply this <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie,</hi> this <hi>promiſe,</hi> to themſelues, wee may chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge it, and finde it verified <hi>literally, ſpiritually,</hi> eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way of theſe Churches of this <hi>State;</hi> wee haue gone through the <hi>fire,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 129.1.2.</note> and through them <hi>water; Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a time haue they afflicted me from my youth vp may England now ſay; many a time haue they afflicted mee from my youth vp: Remember Edom</hi> (may <hi>England</hi> cry) <hi>remember Edom, O God, which ſaid, Downe with it, downe with it, even to the ground; wee will raze out their name and memoriall from vnder Heaven.</hi> True indeede, while wee carried the marke of the <hi>Beaſt in our foreheads,</hi> while wee bare (like <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſſe) that <hi>Balaam of Rome,</hi> and ſuffered his intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable exactions, giuing vp our ſelues, our ſtates, goods, ſoules, as ſlaues and vaſſals of <hi>Antichriſt;</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:4221:18"/> who but the <hi>Engliſh?</hi> Who more favoured at the Court of <hi>Rome?</hi> While our treaſure was <hi>inexhaſtus puteus</hi> (as that Pope ſcoffingly) a <hi>Mine</hi> that could not be <hi>dreined:</hi> that which the <hi>Indies</hi> are to <hi>Spaine,</hi> that was <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> now wee were his <hi>Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes white Sonnes,</hi> he our <hi>Ghoſtly father,</hi> what bleſſing had we from him? What Immunities? What red hattes? What Indulgences? What not? the <hi>Devill ſmiles while he is pleaſed;</hi> but ever ſince the time of <hi>Reformation;</hi> ſo couragiouſly attempted by King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight; ſo devoutly proſecuted by that Noble <hi>Ioſias,</hi> whoſe early holines,<note place="margin">King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth.</note> and timely ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Lord deſerues an everlaſting Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſo happily ſeconded, promoted (after ſome interruption) by our famous <hi>Deborah,</hi> that late <hi>match-leſſe, peere-leſſe Queene of ever bleſſed memory;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Queene</hi> Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth.</note> ſo conſtantly perpetuated, conſummated, and to this day continued by our moſt wiſe and <hi>Renowned Soueraigne Lord,</hi> King IAMES. Ever ſince wee haue ſhaken off that thouſand times worſe then <hi>Egyptian</hi> bondage; ever ſince wee brake off that iron yoke of <hi>Babel,</hi> that ſo long held vs vnder; the <hi>Devill hath ſhewed himſelfe in his likeneſſe;</hi> what Buls haue roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from <hi>Rome?</hi> What Excommunications? What Anathema's haue bin Thundred out by that <hi>Man of ſinne?</hi> What curſings, with Bell, Booke, &amp; Candle? How haue wee beene adiudged for <hi>Heretickes?</hi> ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenced to <hi>flames,</hi> reputed worſe then <hi>Infidels,</hi> then <hi>Dogges.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vide D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hall.</note> One of their <hi>Ieſuites giues vp himſelfe for damnd, if ſuch Heretickes as wee can be ſaued.</hi> How is it made a meritorious Act, a <hi>worke of ſuper-erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,</hi> to murther our <hi>King,</hi> to blow vp our <hi>State,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:4221:19"/> to deſolate and depopulate our <hi>Kingdome.</hi> Many haue beene our Troubles, many and great; many ſecret conſpiracies, many open incurſions, many forraine attempts of enemies abroad, many inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine inſurrections of boſome vipers at home: How long haue wee carried <hi>fire</hi> in our boſomes? and doe not our feete yet tread vpon Scorpions? As many, ſo great haue beene our Troubles. Great enemies were ſtirred vp; <hi>mighty Princes,</hi> the moſt <hi>potent, and puiſſant Kings</hi> of the earth, friends to the Beaſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.</note> how were they enraged? How did <hi>they bandy together againſt the Lord, and againſt his Annointed?</hi> Great Stratagems were laid, even as deepe as Hell, to the vtter ruination, both of <hi>Church and State,</hi> to the finall extirpation of our name and memoriall from vnder Heaven. How oft hath the knife beene at our <hi>throate?</hi> What treaſons? What conſpiracies were hatched in the dayes of our late Queene <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi> (that <hi>wonder of Women,</hi> and <hi>mirrour of her ſex</hi>)? No ſooner was the <hi>fire</hi> quenched in one cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but it breakes forth in another place; no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was one wound cloſed, but another bleeds a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh: Many a time were wee at the pits brinke, and knew it not, deſtinated as <hi>ſheepe to the ſlaughter;</hi> our Land quartered,<note place="margin">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hall <hi>in his</hi> Panygericke.</note> or Doome prophecied; <hi>When that Snow melts</hi> (as they gaue it out triumphantly) <hi>wee ſhall ſee a floud,</hi> and pointed to the <hi>Gray-hayres</hi> of that then <hi>liuing Empreſſe.</hi> But aboue all, two e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeciall dangers (never to be forgotten) did threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten this Nation; never any people vnder Heaven were put to the like ſtraits. You cannot forget that famous Climactericall yeare <hi>Eighty-Eight;</hi> That
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:4221:19"/> 
               <hi>Senacherib</hi> of <hi>Spaine,</hi> how confident was he to haue ſwallowed vs vp quicke at one morſell? How did he preſume to command with his <hi>Invincible Navy</hi> Sea and Land? How did he preſume to put a bridle and make a bridge over the <hi>Ocean,</hi> to over-run this <hi>ſpot of earth</hi> in one inſtant? Now I trow you were in the midſt of the <hi>waters.</hi> This <hi>fifth of November</hi> mindes vs of another pinch as great, if not greater then the former; there wanted but the kindling of a <hi>match,</hi> to haue ſet this Cittie all in a <hi>flame of fire;</hi> this Country and Kingdome all in a <hi>flame of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtion.</hi> Were wee not now in the midſt of the <hi>fire?</hi> If the <hi>Lord had not beene with vs, that water</hi> had over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed all; if the <hi>Lord had not beene with vs, that fire</hi> had beene kindled, and wee all had periſhed in that flame.</p>
            <p>And thus are wee fallen ſuddenly, from the <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> to glance at the <hi>Deliverance,</hi> (bleſſed be That <hi>Iehovah,</hi> that hath linked them ſo together, that wee cannot ſpeake of the one, but wee muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the other.) Now ſince I am fled into this pleaſant field, I will not ſtep backe; but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate you to follow me with your attention, and as you haue taſted of the bitter, ſo now cloſe your Stomacks with the ſweete; which I haue reſerved for the laſt, as being the beſt and chiefeſt matter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for this dayes diſcourſe, and moſt ſutable to the occaſion of our preſent meeting.</p>
            <p>Hitherto you haue heard onely of the <hi>troubles,</hi> now followes the <hi>triumphs</hi> of the <hi>Saints;</hi> wherein was offered to our conſideration, as wee found in the reſolution of the Text.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:4221:20"/>1. The victory it ſelfe, which is acquired; <hi>The flouds ſhall not over-flow thee; the flame ſhall not kindle vpon thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Author of this victory, to whom the <hi>glory of the day</hi> muſt be aſcribed, in thoſe words; <hi>I will be with thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Conqueſt is further commended from the time; <hi>When thou, &amp;c.</hi> It ſhall come <hi>ſeaſonably, oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunely,</hi> when they were in their greateſt difficulties, in their greateſt perplexitie; then, even <hi>then I will be with thee, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The afflictions of <hi>Ioſeph are neuer ſo many, neuer ſo great, but they ſhall find an evaſion.</hi> The Church can never be ſo ſtraitned, but firſt or laſt, it ſhall be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged; the Church can neuer be ſo diſtreſſed, but ſooner or later it ſhall be relieued. Her caſe is oft <hi>dangerous,</hi> never <hi>deſperate.</hi> Let her walke in the <hi>valley of the ſhadow of death</hi> with <hi>David;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 23.4.</note> let her be caſt into the <hi>Denne of Lyons</hi> with <hi>Daniel;</hi> with <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan 6.16.</note> let her be plunged into <hi>the deepe dungeon;</hi> let her be projected with the <hi>Hebrew babes</hi> (as was noted) into the midſt of the waters; with the <hi>three children,</hi> and with thoſe innumerable <hi>troupes of Martyrs,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>midſt of the fire;</hi> what though the members of her body with <hi>Iſaiah</hi> paſſe vnder the Saw? with <hi>Iames,</hi> are cut off by the ſword? let their carkaſſes be mangled and chopt into pieces, their bodies ſcorched, burned, racked, roſted; come what can come,<note place="margin">Premi poteſt eccleſia opprimi non poteſt. <hi>Pſal. 30.5. Pſal. 112.4.</hi>
               </note> the <hi>Iſrael of God</hi> may be <hi>preſſed,</hi> cannot be <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed;</hi> though ſorrow may befall them in the <hi>eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ioy ſhall ariſe in the morning. Vnto the righteous ariſeth light in darkneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:4221:20"/>
            <p>This is the Cloſe, as <hi>David</hi> had learned in the <hi>Schoole of Affliction, Many are the troubles of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, but the Lord delivereth them out of all; delivered</hi> they are not from one, or few, or many, but from <hi>all.</hi> Marke the end of the <hi>vpright man,</hi> his latter <hi>end is Peace;</hi> there may be <hi>ſtormes</hi> in the way, but in the end there will follow an <hi>eternall Calme.</hi> This <hi>Shippe</hi> may be toſſed, cannot be drowned;<note place="margin">Pſal. 112.6.</note> this <hi>Mount Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> may be moved, cannot be removed.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
               </label> Shee hath the word of <hi>Iehovah</hi> to ſecure her, a word more firme then Heaven. The Lord of Hoaſts will come in to her ſuccour, He comes with <hi>ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnder his wings,</hi> He comes in ſeaſonably to helpe at a <hi>dead lift. Mans greateſt extremitie is Gods fitteſt opportunitie;</hi> when no hope in earth, then exſpect helpe from Heaven, then the Almightie comes ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on the Clouds, and <hi>commands deliverance for his Iacob:</hi> let the Sea worke and rage, and boyle and foame, and ſwell vp to Heaven, his word makes <hi>all huſht.</hi> But what doe I preventing my ſelfe? Let vs leaue dilating on this Subject to his proper place; and now make application of the point, and grow to that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion which <hi>this day</hi> doth witneſſe, and proclaime to the whole world.</p>
            <p>Looke backe my Brethren, remember thoſe <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> dayes, that bloudy <hi>Quinqueinium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nero</hi> his <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queinium</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for thoſe ſparkles of humanitie; that of <hi>Q. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> contrary.</note> what a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate pinch were wee brought to in time of that perſecution? What maſſacring? What butchering? What Bonnering? What burning of thoſe chaſt <hi>Virgins</hi> that would not proſtitute their ſoules to that <hi>Whore of Babylon?</hi> that would not licke vp their filthy vomit, diſgorged in the dayes of King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward?</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:4221:21"/> What ſtreets did not flame with <hi>fires?</hi> What faggots did not fry the bones of thoſe miſ-called <hi>Heretickes?</hi> What Citty? What Towne? What Village was not <hi>watered</hi> with the blood,<note place="margin">Sanguis Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrum; ſemen Eccleſiae.</note> 
               <hi>enlightned</hi> with the flames of thoſe conſtant <hi>crowned Martyrs?</hi> The mercies of the wicked are cruell, (as the wiſe King obſerues,) as thoſe barbarous ſavage Tyger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrants, made it too true, who to ſhew themſelues more mercileſſe then the mercileſſe Elements (fire and water) retorted that <hi>Infant</hi> into the <hi>Mothers flames,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fox in his <hi>Acts</hi> &amp; <hi>Mon.</hi>
               </note> which the very fire as a <hi>mercifull Midwife</hi> had delivered from the <hi>Mothers wombe.</hi> Now they inſulted, cracking what a ſure foundation was laid for vnder-ſetting, and propping vp their newly <hi>repaired wals of Iericho;</hi> now they applaud their owne wits, that had vndermined the <hi>Goſpel</hi> (vnder the name of <hi>Hereſie</hi>) ſo as it ſhould never be able to peepe forth, or hold vp head in the profeſſors thereof.</p>
            <p>Thus when all was deſperate in the eye of fleſh, how ſuddainly was the ſtreame turned?<note place="margin">So the Father of <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtate; <hi>nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becula eſt cito tranſibit.</hi>
               </note> how ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly was that ſtorme of blood blowne over? their high wals ſo lately daubed vp with vntempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red morter, how did they fall in a moment, being quaſhed to powder? and themſelues with all their rubbidge ſent packing over Seas. What a deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate exigent were we brought to, when that ſtrange <hi>Horned Moone</hi> appeared on our Coaſtes; when that <hi>Invincicle Armado</hi> of <hi>Spaine</hi> (as <hi>they ſtiled it</hi>) was ready to encircle our Nation.<note place="margin">Their ſhippes were caſt into the forme of a halfe-Moone.</note> The enemy like that great <hi>Levi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>than</hi> had in conceit drawne vp our <hi>Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan</hi> into his <hi>noſtrils,</hi> ſo had he devoured vs in his
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:4221:21"/> hopes, that already <hi>(ante victoriam triump hum canit)</hi> he ſings the Triumph before a ſtroake was ſtricken; and at the putting on of his Armour,<note place="margin">The Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </note> boaſts as he that puts it off. The mother of <hi>Siſera</hi> looked out at the Window, and cryed through the Latteſſe;<note place="margin">Iud. 5.28.29.30.</note> 
               <hi>Why is his Chariot ſo long in comming? Why tarry the Wheeles of his Chariot: Her wiſe Ladies anſwered, yea, ſhee turned and anſwered her ſelfe; haue they not ſped, haue they not divided the prey to euery man a damoſell or two? to Siſera a prey of divers colours, of divers co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours needle-worke, fit for the neckes of them that take the ſpoile.</hi> Thus they ſolaced themſelues, when loe how all their hopes vaniſhed into ſmoake. The <hi>Sunne, Moone,</hi> and <hi>Starres</hi> in their courſes, the <hi>windes, waters,</hi> all fight for our <hi>England.</hi> The Lord over-throwes the horſe and his rider, and drownes this <hi>blazing Comet</hi> in the wide <hi>Ocean,</hi> which drew the eyes of all the world to ſee the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of that <hi>prodigeous meteor,</hi> that as ſome dreamed, others feared, <hi>Babylon</hi> wiſhed, preſaged a <hi>fatall peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od</hi> to the <hi>Engliſh Iſle and Empire.</hi> So true is the word of the Lord by his Prophet; <hi>WEE paſſed through the water, yet did not the flouds over-flow vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What a deſperate pinch were wee brought to this <hi>fifth day of November?</hi> Now wee were in the <hi>fire</hi> indeed; a <hi>fire</hi> kindled in <hi>Hell,</hi> a ſulphurean <hi>fire,</hi> into which not <hi>Three Children,</hi> but the <hi>Three States of our Realme,</hi> were enwrapped and all bound together, to haue periſhed with one cracke. Let vs pauſe here, and conſider the Danger of our <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie,</hi> that wee may be ſtirred vp the more fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, and heartily, to magnifie the mercy, power,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:4221:22"/> and goodneſſe of the <hi>Lord,</hi> manifeſted in out <hi>deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <head>Conſider</head>
               <item>How cunningly it was contrived.</item>
               <item>How cruelly it was intended.</item>
               <item>How nearly atchieued.</item>
               <item>How miraculouſly diſcovered.</item>
            </list>
            <p>For the cunning in contriving; what ſecrecy of <hi>place?</hi> What ſecrecy of <hi>perſon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The place, a <hi>place of darkeneſſe,</hi> and therefore fit for a worke of darkeneſſe; the ſecrecy of the place ſeemed to invite them to this bloody deſigne; even as the opportunitie of <hi>time,</hi> ſmiled vpon them, and promiſed to be the vnhappie Midwife to deliver the Actors (now bigge with their conception) of this monſtrous burden. Let me now take you hand in hand, and lead you to this <hi>darke Caue,</hi> this <hi>hollow denne,</hi> this <hi>fiery Aetna,</hi> this <hi>tormenting Tophet;</hi> I know not what to call it, <hi>Grammar, Logicke, Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke,</hi> all are poſed, no <hi>Art</hi> can yeeld a word empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall enough for this <hi>Artificiall Phalarian invention.</hi> A <hi>ſtrange Engin,</hi> it was invented for the torment of Innocents, but (as that of <hi>Phaleris</hi>) turned to the torment of the Inventors. See here what <hi>Barrels of Powder</hi> packed cloſe together? What <hi>piles of wood</hi> billetted over thoſe Barrels? What <hi>barres of iron</hi> mingled with thoſe piles? Of all reſemblances me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinkes a <hi>Tophet</hi> ſits it beſt; See the deſcription of <hi>Tophet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 30.33.</note> and paralell them. <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 30.33. <hi>Tophet is ordained of old, yea for the King it is prepared, he hath made it deepe and large, the pile thereof is fire and much wood, the breath of the Lord like a ſtreame of brimſtone
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:4221:22"/> doth kindle it.</hi> Loe here a right <hi>Tophet,</hi> ordained of old, hatched in the latter yeares of the raigne of our late Queene <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> prepared not by <hi>God,</hi> but by <hi>Men;</hi> not by <hi>Men,</hi> but by <hi>Devils;</hi> Was it not dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged deepe? and made large, made for the <hi>King,</hi> yea and <hi>Queene, Prince, Prelates, Lords, Commons, all;</hi> the burning of it was fire and much wood, a <hi>ſtreame of Powder,</hi> as a river of brimſton was to kindle it, a right <hi>Tophet.</hi> Some place <hi>Hell</hi> in the Center or midſt of the earth, here you might haue found it ſomewhat beneath the ſuperficies of the earth. Thus were their villanies buried in the bowels of the earth,<note place="margin">Iſa. 29.15.</note> 
               <hi>they digge deepe to hide their Councell from God and Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The perſons will be as ſecret as the place; theſe <hi>Catholike</hi> conſpirators, to make all ſure, to ſowe their lips faſt, ſweare a ſilene, and binde that <hi>Oath with the Sacrament.</hi> O flagitious vnheard-of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie! God himſelfe (will he, nill he) muſt haue as much as in them lay, an hand in this <hi>tranſcendent Treaſon;</hi> let no man henceforth wonder at the fury of that <hi>Romiſh Cataline,</hi> who forced his followers to pledge each other in <hi>Healths of humane blood.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold here that <hi>Romiſh Catesby,</hi> with his Complices, take the <hi>Blood of God</hi> (at leaſt his <hi>Body</hi>) and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they maintaine it, the <hi>reall eſſentiall blood of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of God</hi> muſt be <hi>carouſed,</hi> to glue vp their lip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the diſcovery of this <hi>Helliſh Deſigne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus cloſely and covertly was it carried, ſo lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in the mantle of darkeneſſe, that none but the Devill as they gaue it out <hi>(the Lord was farre from
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:4221:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> their thoughts)</hi> could <hi>vnvaile</hi> it, and plucke off the <hi>maske</hi> from this <hi>Hagge;</hi> yet was their crueltie no whit inferior to their ſecrecy. Let me begin in the words of <hi>Moſes;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 4.32.</note> 
               <hi>Aske of the dayes of old that haue bin ſince God created man vpon the earth, from one end of Heaven vnto the other, if there came to paſſe ſuch a great thing as this, or ever the like was heard of;</hi> Search all <hi>Chronicles,</hi> turne over the <hi>Records</hi> of all Nations; no age, no ſtory, humane or divine, can match this matchleſſe preſident, ſo that wee may well take vp the Heathen <hi>Poets</hi> complaint.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Audax, omnia perpeti gens humana</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vetitum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> nefas.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam 16. 2 Sam. 15.31.</note>The <hi>Treaſon of Abſolon;</hi> the <hi>Conſpiracy of Achito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel;</hi> the <hi>Coniuration of Cataline;</hi> the <hi>Machination of Haman,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſth. 3.8.</note> to roote out the whole Nation of the <hi>Iewes;</hi> the <hi>Maſſacre of France;</hi> the <hi>ſlaughter of the Indies;</hi> wherein worldes of people were moſt cruelly made away: all hainous tranſcendent crimes, all fall ſhort of this <hi>Nero</hi> that <hi>Spung of Bloud and Monſter of Men,</hi> as the Stories record, wiſhed, all the people of <hi>Rome</hi> had had but one head, that he might chop it off at a blow; that which was but deſired of <hi>Nero,</hi> was not wiſhed onely, but plotted, and attempted by theſe <hi>Sanguineous Antichriſtian Neroes,</hi> had their plot taken effect, not the <hi>head of Rome,</hi> but of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> had beene cut off at a <hi>Blow. Nero</hi> cauſed the Citie of <hi>Rome</hi> to be <hi>fired,</hi> and laid the blame on the <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> If their traine had blowne vp our <hi>Church</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:4221:23"/> and <hi>State,</hi> the imputation of ſo foule a fact by theſe equivocating <hi>Catholikes,</hi> muſt haue beene caſt on the <hi>Puritans. Three famous kingdomes</hi> by a <hi>bleſſed Peace-maker,</hi> vnited into one <hi>happy Monarchy, Vno actu tactu ictu, with one blow, and blaſt in a day, an houre, a moment, had periſhed,</hi> ere they knew who hurt them: no ſect, no ſex, no perſon, nor age might be ſpared, no not thoſe of their owne Religion, the <hi>Powder,</hi> like the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Medina</hi> his <hi>Sword,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theſe be your chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>would haue knowne no difference betweene Proteſtant and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt.</hi> The <hi>Kings Maieſtie,</hi> the <hi>Golden Head</hi> of this Land, the <hi>Lords Annointed,</hi> and the <hi>breath of our no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils;</hi> His deare <hi>Queene,</hi> the Roote that bare ſo roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſtems; His <hi>Princely heire,</hi> the pledge of our ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding hopes; the <hi>Honorable Councell,</hi> the <hi>eye of our Land,</hi> the Noble <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Baron,</hi> the <hi>Shields</hi> and <hi>ſhoulders</hi> of our Land, the <hi>Reverend Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Cleargie,</hi> the <hi>Chariots and Horſemen of Iſrael;</hi> the graue <hi>Sages</hi> and <hi>Iudges,</hi> the <hi>Handes</hi> of our Land for execution of Iuſtice; the <hi>flower</hi> of our <hi>Gentry</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> the <hi>feete</hi> of this Land; roote and branch, Prieſt and people; <hi>Head, roote, branches, eyes, ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, armes, tongues, handes, feete, all,</hi> all ſhould haue beene torne vp and mounted on high, to fall head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, their carkaſſes mangled, the ſheepe brained and burnt by an <hi>vnheard-of kinde of execution.</hi> In their wrath they digged downe a wall, and in their anger would take away a whole nation as one man, <hi>Curſed be their anger for it was fierce, and their wrath for it was cruell; into their ſecrets let not the righteous enter, my ſoule be not thou ioyned with their Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:4221:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>How neare was it come? even to the point of exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution? the <hi>Children were at the birth;</hi> wee had but the burning of a <hi>match</hi> to liue; not a <hi>haires-breadth</hi> betweene vs and this <hi>Death,</hi> theſe <hi>flames.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How miraculouſly was the plot diſcovered rod? how opportunely were the traytors defeated? the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the <hi>King came from the inſpiration of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie;</hi> ſtrange it is to conſider, what <hi>Engliſh</hi> his <hi>Maieſty</hi> did pick out of a <hi>dark and Aenigmaticall let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> going againſt all Grammaticall conſtruction; He that ſits in Heaven, made their owne handes and Pens to bewray all; ſo the <hi>Preacher, Curſe not the King,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 10.20.</note> 
               <hi>no not in thy thought, for the fowle of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſhall carry it; and that which hath wings ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the matter.</hi> If the Lord had not now beene with vs,<note place="margin">Prov. 16.10.</note> among vs, for vs, and put a <hi>word of Divina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into the lippes of our gratious Soveraigne,</hi> wee had all beene long ere this <hi>as Sodom and Gomorrha. King, Prince, Noble, Peeres, Prelates, Iudges, Gentry, Commons; Our peace, plentie, the Goſpel of peace (the comfort of our liues, and the life of all our comforts) all had vaniſhed into Aſh-heapes.</hi> Thus am I fallen vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Author</hi> of this Great Deliverance; who kept vs in this <hi>fire, that the flame did not ſo much as kindle vpon vs.</hi> So <hi>literally</hi> are the words of this <hi>Prophecie</hi> fulfilled of this <hi>Church and State,</hi> who kept vs? <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah,</hi> ſaith my Text, <hi>Iehovah</hi> ſaith this day; <hi>I will be with thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>ſafetie of the Church conſiſts in the preſence of the Lord. Iehovah</hi> is that <hi>Cloud</hi> which giues light to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 14.25.</note> ſtrikes terror into the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:4221:24"/> takes off the <hi>Wheeles of their Chariots. Iehovah</hi> is that <hi>Wall</hi> of <hi>fire</hi> that fenceth his elect, and conſumes his enemies; the Lord is my <hi>Rocke,</hi> my <hi>Fortreſſe,</hi> ſo <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid. The name of the Lord is a ſtrong Tower,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 18.10.</note> 
               <hi>into which the righteous Nation ſhall enter,</hi> ſo <hi>Salomon.</hi> This <hi>Tower</hi> is invincible, this <hi>Bulwarke</hi> impregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; this <hi>Fortreſſe</hi> is <hi>out of Gun-ſhot,</hi> and therefore cannot be battered; this <hi>Wall</hi> reacheth higher then the <hi>Heavens,</hi> and therefore cannot be ſcaled. The Lord is ever with his <hi>Church,</hi> what he ſpeaks of the <hi>Temple,</hi> the type of the <hi>Church;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 28.20.</note> needs muſt it be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified of the <hi>Church,</hi> the <hi>truth</hi> of that <hi>type.</hi> 2 Chro. 7.16. <hi>I haue choſen this place, that my name may be there for ever, and mine eyes, and my heart ſhall be there perpetually.</hi> There is he preſent and reſident, and that not as a naked <hi>Spectator,</hi> to behold their miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, but as a <hi>tender Father, as a mightie Sauiour.</hi> As a <hi>tender Father,</hi> commiſerating their diſtreſſes, caring the cares, grieuing the griefes, and fearing the feares of his choſen;<note place="margin">Iſa. 63.9.</note> 
               <hi>In all their troubles he is troubled.</hi> When the <hi>foote</hi> was trod vpon in earth, the <hi>Head</hi> cryes from <hi>Heaven, Saul, Saul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts. 9.4.</note> 
               <hi>why perſecuteſt thou me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He is preſent, ſecondly, as an <hi>Almightie power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Saviour;</hi> is there any thing <hi>too hard for him?</hi> Is his <hi>arme ſhortned?</hi> Did not he <hi>wound Rahab?</hi> Smite the <hi>Dragon,</hi> overthrow <hi>the horſe and his rider,</hi> make a <hi>path in the great Water,</hi> and <hi>allay the heate of the fire?</hi> He works <hi>with meanes, without meanes, againſt means,</hi> and <hi>doth what ever he will in heaven or earth</hi> Hath not he ſet bounds to the Sea,<note place="margin">Iob. 38.11.</note> though it <hi>rage and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:4221:25"/> foame, here it muſt ſtay, thus farre it ſhall come, and no farther, here the proud waues muſt be broken.</hi> Hath not he <hi>Satan</hi> in a chaine,<note place="margin">Iob. 1.</note> and all his inſtruments, that they cannot plucke a <hi>haire</hi> from the head of his ſervants, without his leaue and licence?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label>
               <note place="margin">Si Deus nobiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, quis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra nos? <hi>Rom. 8.31.</hi>
               </note>Behold now the ſafetie, the ſecuritie of the Church: if <hi>God be with vs, who ſhall be against vs?</hi> If <hi>God be with vs, what need we feare what man can doe vnto vs, men</hi> or <hi>Devils?</hi> No maruaile if the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet command, <hi>feare not.</hi> He that is thus <hi>guided,</hi> thus <hi>guarded,</hi> how can he feare or faint? So the ſame Prophet,<note place="margin">Iſa. 51.12.13</note> Chap. 51. Verſ. 12.13. <hi>I, even I am he that comfort thee, who art thou that thou ſhouldeſt be afraid of a man, and of the ſonne of man, which ſhall be made as graſſe; and forgetteſt the Lord thy Maker, &amp;c. Iehovah</hi> hath vndertaken to be the <hi>Lord Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector,</hi> or <hi>Lord-keeper of his Red vine.</hi> Iſaiah. 27.3. <hi>I the Lord doe watch over it by night and by day;</hi> Hee will defend it againſt <hi>ſecret trecheries,</hi> theſe are <hi>night</hi>-aſſaults; againſt <hi>open Hoſtilities,</hi> theſe are <hi>day</hi>-aſſaults. What though the <hi>Ramping</hi> Lyon goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout continually,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.8.</note> ſeeking whom he may devoure? Is not the <hi>Lyon of the Tribe of Iudah</hi> as vigilant to defend, as <hi>Satan</hi> to aſſault? The <hi>deſtroyer of Iſrael</hi> never ſlumbreth nor ſleepeth; no <hi>more doth the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 121.4.</note> he <hi>alſo never ſleepeth, never ſlumbreth.</hi> Let their enemies be never ſo <hi>many,</hi> all <hi>nations to him are but as the duſt of the Balance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 40.15.</note> 
               <hi>the drop of a Bucket, as nothing, leſſe then naught.</hi> Let their enemies be never ſo <hi>mightie,</hi> he hath their <hi>hearts</hi> in his hand, can turne them as the <hi>Rivers of waters,</hi> and make
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:4221:25"/> our <hi>enemies at peace with vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 33.4.</note> changing their <hi>ſtabs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to kiſſes:</hi> he hath their <hi>heads</hi> in his hand, and can infatuate the <hi>wilieſt Herod,</hi> the <hi>craftieſt Achitophel,</hi> turning their <hi>Councells into folly;</hi> he hath their <hi>Hands and Hornes</hi> in his hand, and can either <hi>binde them to their good behaviour,</hi> or knocke out the <hi>Teeth of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> before they <hi>bite;</hi> let them <hi>digge dippe,</hi> to hide their <hi>plots,</hi> the Lord will goe beyond them; let them <hi>ioyne hand to hand, they ſhall not proſper:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 11.21.</note> Wee may ſay it, wee may ſweare it, wee muſt beleeue it, wee haue had experience (never any Church more of the like) what it is to haue ſuch a <hi>Protector,</hi> whoſe <hi>power is vnreſiſtable,</hi> his <hi>will vnchangeable,</hi> his <hi>skill vnſearchable;</hi> whoſe <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> is ſuch, that he can doe what he will; whoſe <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> is ſuch, that he will doe what he can; and ever magnifie both his <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> and <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> in the <hi>protection of his Iſrael,</hi> and in the <hi>converſion</hi> or <hi>confuſion</hi> of his <hi>enemies.</hi> Witneſſe <hi>this</hi> day of dayes: on the <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> of our <hi>fifth of November,</hi> they would haue <hi>blowne vs vp;</hi> on the <hi>evening</hi> of their <hi>fifth of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember,</hi> God <hi>beate them downe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Is <hi>Iehovah</hi> the <hi>Deliverer of his Iſrael?</hi> Why let God then haue the <hi>Honor</hi> of his owne worke; not our <hi>wit,</hi> not our <hi>wealth,</hi> not our <hi>goodnes,</hi> not our <hi>greatnes,</hi> not our <hi>friends,</hi> not our <hi>Bulwarkes,</hi> but the <hi>Lord onely; it was the Lords doing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 118.23.24.</note> 
               <hi>let it euer be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueilous in our eyes:</hi> This is the <hi>Day which the Lord hath made, let vs be glad and reioyce.</hi> Let the <hi>wicked Politician,</hi> the <hi>Machivilian Atheiſt ſacrifice to their owne nets.</hi> We will cry with that <hi>Kingly Prophet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 115.1.</note> not
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:4221:26"/> 
               <hi>vnto vs, not vs ô Lord, but vnto thy Name, wee giue the glory. (Totum hoc quatumcunque ſit quod certè miximum eſt, totum eſt tuum)</hi> the whole prayſe of ſo <hi>glorious a reſcue,</hi> how great ſo euer it be, which indeede is exceeding great, is onely due to <hi>Iehovah.</hi> Let the <hi>King ſay it is the Lord that giueth great deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances vnto his David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 18.</note> 
               <hi>and ſheweth mercy to his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed, and his ſeede for ever.</hi> Let the <hi>Great Peeres</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> ſay it is not our <hi>Arme</hi> that hath ſaued vs, not our <hi>mighty ſtrength,</hi> but the <hi>Strength of Iſrael Iehovah.</hi> Let the <hi>Houſe of Aaron</hi> ſay and ſing <hi>prayſes,</hi> ſing <hi>prayſes</hi> vnto the <hi>Lord</hi> that hath <hi>done wiſely,</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered our enemies, <hi>broken their ſnares,</hi> and we are eſcaped.<note place="margin">Pſ. 124.1.2.3.</note> Let all <hi>England</hi> ſay if the <hi>Lord, had not beene on our ſide, if the Lord had not beene on our ſide, when men roſe vp againſt vs, they had ſwallowed vs vp quicke, when their wrath was kindled againſt vs.</hi> Praiſe waiteth for thee <hi>O God in Sion,</hi> who is like <hi>our God who doth great and wondrous thinges.</hi> Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for euer be that <hi>Noble and Honorable Society (The High Court of Parliament)</hi> that to all ages hath ſet a <hi>Day</hi> apart, for the <hi>Honor of that God,</hi> who is the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector</hi> of his <hi>Sion,</hi> the <hi>Detector</hi> the <hi>Deſtroyer</hi> of his and their <hi>implacable enemies:</hi> Goe on ſtill <hi>O Noble Senate,</hi> let <hi>King, Prince, Peeres, Prelats, Commons,</hi> all conſpire to <hi>honor the God of heaven</hi> by enacting ſuch <hi>ſolemne Panagerickes to Iehovah;</hi> and the <hi>God of honor</hi> will honor <hi>You, this Church, this State, your Poſterity;</hi> the <hi>Generation to come,</hi> ſhall bleſſe God for the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance of this Day; for the Record of this Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance, for this <hi>publicke gratulation</hi> vpon Record.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:4221:26"/> Bleſſed be that <hi>God</hi> which hath put it into the <hi>heart of that Great Aſſembly,</hi> with an vnanimous and free conſent to enact it for a <hi>Law in Iſrael, and an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance in Iacob for euer.</hi> If euer we forget this mercy, <hi>let our tongues cleaue to the roofe of our mouthes,</hi> and our armes <hi>rott</hi> from our <hi>ſhoulders, Let all faithfull, loyall, true hearted Engliſh Proteſtants, with one heart and voice cry, Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, doth the ſecurity of the Church, State, all, lie in the preſence of God? Where God is, there is no danger; as where hee is nor, no ſafetie; O keepe him while we haue him, driue him not from you, who is our <hi>Buckler, our ſhield,</hi> all in all vnto vs: keepe him in his Word, in his Sabboths, in his Ordinances, and he will keepe you. Would you know in a word, what driues the Lord from a land, a people, <hi>ſinne;</hi> nothing but <hi>ſinne</hi> can doe it, and <hi>ſinne</hi> will doe it;<note place="margin">Iſa. 59.2.</note> 
               <hi>your ſinnes haue ſeperated betweene me and you;</hi> where <hi>ſinne</hi> is countenanced, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, multiplied, there is no <hi>Harbor</hi> for the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty. He is a God of purer eyes then to behold iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, what communion betweene God and Beliall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hab. 1.13.</note>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.14.15.</note> 
               <hi>light and darkeneſſe, Chriſt and Antichriſt? Sinne</hi> chaſes the Lord away, and leaues that perſon, that Nation naked, vnfenced, expoſed to the <hi>malice</hi> of men, to the <hi>fury</hi> of <hi>Satan,</hi> to the <hi>flames</hi> of hell. Every wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>ſinner</hi> is a <hi>Traytor</hi> to <hi>God, his King, and Countrey,</hi> as well as to his owne <hi>ſoule.</hi> Away with <hi>beloued dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſinnes:</hi> away with thoſe waſting <hi>King-killing State-ruinating ſinnes: Idolatry, contempt of Gods
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:4221:27"/> word, worſhip, Sacraments, Sabbath, Miniſters; ſcandalous</hi> enormous impieties, <hi>out-facing Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie;</hi> theſe if they ſhould be found among vs, will kindle a <hi>flame</hi> in our Citie, Countrey, a worſe then <hi>Powder-flame,</hi> that ſhall burne to the bottome of hell.</p>
            <p>If we our ſelues betray not our <hi>ſoules,</hi> our <hi>Church,</hi> our <hi>State,</hi> our <hi>Kingdome,</hi> in vaine ſhall the <hi>Gates of Rome</hi> repine at the proſperitie of <hi>England;</hi> if wee pull not downe our owne walls with our owne handes, no <hi>Engins of theirs</hi> ſhall ever batter them; if wee doe not open the <hi>ſluces,</hi> and <hi>floud-gates,</hi> the Invndations of that <hi>Romiſh Nilus,</hi> with her <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh waters,</hi> ſhall never over-flow our bankes; If wee carry not Flax, Tinder, <hi>Gun-powder,</hi> in our owne boſomes, and ſtrike not fire with our owne fingers, their <hi>matches</hi> ſhall never take, their <hi>ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles</hi> ſhall not burne, the <hi>flame ſhall not kindle vpon vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For Gods-ſake therefore, for your ſoules-ſake, for your Countreys-ſake; if you loue your <hi>King, Countrey, peace, plentie, the Goſpell of peace, your goods, friends, children,</hi> away with the toleration, diſpenſation of knowne, groſſe, ſcandalous, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, enormous Impieties; maintaine a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall correſpondence with your <hi>Heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> be in league with <hi>Heaven;</hi> delight to <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him, his Name, Word, Worſhippe, Sacraments, Sabbaths, Meſſengers,</hi> that hee may delight to <hi>Watch</hi> over you; <hi>Serue</hi> him who <hi>ſaved</hi> vs, and therefore <hi>ſaved</hi> vs (that wee being redeemed
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:4221:27"/> from the handes of our enemies, ſuch ſubtle, cruell, barbarous, ſavage enemies) might <hi>ſerue</hi> him without feare all the dayes of our life, in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe before him. Bleſſed are the people, who are in ſuch a caſe, <hi>who haue the Lord for their God.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
